<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[John's Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[Musings about startups, design and data]]></description><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com</link><image><url>https://www.jmilinovich.com/icon.png</url><title>John&apos;s Blog</title><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 02:43:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.jmilinovich.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[2020 John Milinovich]]></copyright><language><![CDATA[en]]></language><managingEditor><![CDATA[jrmilinovich@gmail.com]]></managingEditor><webMaster><![CDATA[jrmilinovich@gmail.com]]></webMaster><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[My biggest product strategy lesson learned from operating and selling URX (YC S13)]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>It’s been one year since I was a startup founder/CEO. On May 2, 2016, we announced Pinterest’s acquisition of URX and began the next step in our journey. In that moment it was hard to comprehend how different this chapter would be from the one before it, and I’m grateful that I’ve gained some of this perspective over the last year.</p>
<p>In short- <strong>my biggest learning about product strategy from URX is the importance of aligning your vision with your business model.</strong> As with so many things in life, there’s a big difference between understanding things with your head, and knowing them with your heart. I think this is especially true for the “resilient founder” persona who has the fortitude to endure the endless sea of challenges that plague early stage startups.</p>
<p>To call the URX journey anything other than magnificent would be an understatement. I learned more than I could have ever imagined from that 3.5 year period — from raising capital to hiring executives, managing managers of managers to setting the right goals — I am simply not the same person as I was before URX. There are many great resources for founders that outline <a href="http://blog.ycombinator.com/how-not-to-fail/">how to not fail</a>, and what to do when it’s <a href="https://justinkan.com/the-founders-guide-to-selling-your-company-a1b2025c9481?gi=58f6ac561735">time to sell</a>, so instead of rehashing what’s already been said I want to share my most unintuitive lesson learned from operating URX so that you don’t have to learn it the hard way.</p>
<h1 id="theevolutionofurxsbusinessmodel">The Evolution of URX’s Business Model</h1>
<p>URX was one of the first mobile deep linking companies. For the uninitiated, deep linking helps create links into apps so that they can work in a similar way to the web. Without deep links, apps can only be opened to the “top” of the app, which means that the foundation of the internet — hyperlinks — can’t work for apps. This created countless broken experiences for users (how many times have you clicked on a link in an email that took you to the mobile web instead of an app?), and we believed that this was a big opportunity for a startup to solve. We believed that if you could be the company that helps apps succeed with deep linking you could build a comprehensive (and proprietary) understanding of the content inside apps, which would let you create a new paradigm for contextual mobile discovery. We firmly believed that mobile devices would be better if they understood your context and could help you seamlessly navigate across apps based on your intent.</p>
<p>To realize this vision, the first product we built was an SDK and click server that would help an app developer get started using deep links. Developers quickly started adopting this service, but it wasn’t clear this was something they’d be willing to pay for. In talking to our users, we learned that a major use case for deep linking was mobile ad retargeting. The only type of mobile advertising available at the time was “cost per install” based advertising, but with deep links you could actually start running re-engagement campaigns, and retarget your users across apps to bring them back into your app. To validate this insight we started pitching a mobile retargeting solution, and it turns out people wanted this: by YC Demo Day, we had AirBnB, LivingSocial, SideCar and HotelTonight as clients. We <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2013/10/16/urx-ads/">raised a $3.1M seed round</a>, and were on our way.</p>
<p>Over the next 6 months we continued to scale our mobile retargeting business, and <a href="http://blog.ycombinator.com/urx-yc-s13-raises-12-dollars-million-sets-sights-on-links-inside-apps/">raised a $12M Series A</a> to continue expanding our team and our ads business. We capitalized on the press to launch the second version of our free deep linking product OmniLinks to help accelerate developer adoption of our platform. The team was happy, and we were motivated with this new influx of capital to continue working on our mission. However, about 2 months later we started to hit some serious scaling bottlenecks. We were running our ads through third party aggregators (<a href="https://digiday.com/media/wtf-supply-side-platform/">SSPs</a> like MoPub, OpenX and Smaato), which meant that there was no quality controls (our top inventory sources were the Chive and Grindr) and we couldn’t understand a user’s context when seeing an ad. Because of this, we weren’t able to fulfill our advertisers’ budgets or hit their goals at scale. To solve this problem and begin fulfilling our mission of contextual mobile discovery, we believed we would have to become an ad network and go start selling publishers in addition to advertisers. So, that’s what we did. We spent the next 4 months building our contextual ad serving stack, signed up our first publishers up and <a href="https://www.recode.net/2015/4/15/11561474/urx-looks-to-make-its-deep-links-pay-off-with-new-ad-type">officially launched AppViews</a> with a host of great mobile publishers.</p>
<p>In retrospect, by becoming an ad network <strong>we misaligned our business model with our vision of contextual app discovery</strong>. When you’re operating a media business, your success metrics are very different from a discovery/search company. Instead of being purely “user first”, we had to delicately balance the needs of end-users with those of publishers and advertisers, which were very frequently not the same. We had set very real expectations with our customers and board that we would continue to aggressively grow revenue, which forced us to make decisions that were not inline with our mission. This caused a few important moments where we had to make product decisions that felt inauthentic towards our vision, but were required to execute on our business model. By the time we had realized that we chose the wrong business model to support our mission, it was too late for us to change it. Whether we liked it or not, we had customers relying on our product, and set our revenue goals around scaling our media business.</p>
<h1 id="howtotellifyourbusinessmodelandmissionaremisaligned">How to tell if your business model and mission are misaligned</h1>
<p>The best way to make sure your business stays inline with your mission is by making sure your mission statement fully encapsulates the value you want to deliver to your customers, not just the product/technology you want to build. If you get this wrong, you might not end up building the business you want to build.</p>
<p>To tell if your business model and mission are misaligned, go through the exercise of asking yourself these questions regularly:</p>
<p>To achieve our mission:</p>
<ol>
<li>What are the various products or technologies that we could build?</li>
<li>Who is the primary benefactor of this product(s)?</li>
<li>What is the most ideal way we would make money?</li>
</ol>
<p>If we’re successful in executing our current business plan:</p>
<ol>
<li>What is the specific pain point we solve for our customers?</li>
<li>What is the impact our company has on the world?</li>
<li>What is our strategic differentiator within the market?</li>
</ol>
<p>If we’re successful in achieving our mission:</p>
<ol>
<li>What is the specific pain point we solve for our customers?</li>
<li>What is the impact our company has on the world?</li>
<li>What is our strategic differentiator within the market?</li>
</ol>
<p>The goal of asking these questions is to identify the gaps/misalignments between the near- and long-term viewpoints on your business. No company has ever been able to constantly pivot its value prop to create its strategic differentiator. The most successful tech companies of all time have been able to expand upon the same customer pain point and value prop through the duration of their business:</p>
<ul>
<li>Google still helps people search for answers to their questions</li>
<li>AirBnB still helps people make supplemental income by renting their houses</li>
<li>Pinterest still helps people discover and do things they love</li>
<li>Netflix still helps people watch movies in their homes</li>
</ul>
<p>In order to create lasting value for your business and your customers, you have to make sure that your near- and long-term goals are inline with each other. This is a difficult balance to maintain, but is arguably one of the most important things you can do to ensure your company’s success.</p>
<h1 id="whattodoifyouremisaligned">What to do if you’re misaligned</h1>
<p>In answering these questions if you identify a misalignment between your business model and your mission, it’s time for you make some decisions. Ultimately- <strong>do you change your business model, or do you change your mission?</strong> There’s no universally correct answer here, as this is largely stage dependent.</p>
<h2 id="changingyourbusinessmodel">Changing your business model</h2>
<ul>
<li>If you have an established business, changing your business model creates serious customer risk and is probably not the right idea. In this case, you should evaluate changing your mission to better reflect your current business model.</li>
<li>If you have a nascent business, changing your business model is something you can validate by talking to your existing/prospective customers. How is each business model perceived by your customers? Is one more preferable than the other?</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="changingyourmissionstatement">Changing your mission statement</h2>
<ul>
<li>If you have an established business, what would the impact be to your team if you change your mission statement? If you’re a mission driven culture, do you risk attrition if you change your mission? Talk to your executive team to get their feedback on this.</li>
<li>If you have a nascent business, your mission statement should be considered a “work in progress” that is likely to change as you learn more about your customers.</li>
</ul>
<p>Maintaining state between the near- and long-term identify of your business is one of the most difficult jobs of any founder. You only have one chance at a first impression, and getting this right will help create a cohesive story for your company to employees, recruits, customers and investors. If you get this wrong, you will find yourself in a constant identify crisis, which will consistently cause confusion and may never be able to be corrected.</p>]]></description><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/urx-lesson</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/urx-lesson</guid><category><![CDATA[Dan Abramov]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[John Milinovich]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 02:38:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to ace your YC interview]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>Spring has sprung, and the smell of fresh YC applications is in the air. It’s that special time that happens twice a year where thousands of budding entrepreneurs vie for a spot in the upcoming Y Combinator class.</p>
<p>For those among you who are preparing for your interviews over the next few days, I wanted to share some of the best practices that helped Andrew, Nate, James and me pass our interview and earn URX’s place in the Summer 2013 batch.</p>
<h1 id="quickconciseanswersarekey">Quick, concise answers are key</h1>
<p>Each interview lasts about 10 minutes and the interviewers’ goal is to get as much signal about the team as possible. Because of this, the interviews are structured as a series of rapid fire questions that will cover a lot of ground. Having well prepared, concise answers that you can recall quickly is probably the single strongest indicator of success for your interview. We prepared for this by coming up with a list of ~50 expected questions, each with their own with 2–3 bullet point response. Then, we spent hours grilling each other and loaded them into a flashcard webapp for self testing. This took some time, but was well worth it.</p>
<h1 id="knowyour5pointsandmakesureyouspeaktothem">Know your 5 points, and make sure you speak to them</h1>
<p>In any interview, it’s crucial that your personal narrative shines through. Unfortunately, the rapid fire nature of YC interviews makes this difficult. In your prep, it’s crucial that you identify the 3-5 most important points about your business/team that you need the YC interviewers to hear. These can be things about your backgrounds, user growth, revenue, or the like, and together should tell the best version of your story. For our team, these were:</p>
<ol>
<li>We’ve known each other for a long time, and have lots of experience in the space.</li>
<li>We’ve already built the first version of our product</li>
<li>We already have customers</li>
<li>We know what we want to get out of YC</li>
</ol>
<p>We entered our interview with these points ingrained into our heads, and it was my personal mission to make sure we hit on each of them. Sometimes, this was straightforward because the interviewer would ask a related question. Other times, this was more difficult but overall really helped us guide the conversation in the way we wanted it to go.</p>
<h1 id="eachpanelsstyleisdifferentbutbereadytogetgrilled">Each panel’s style is different, but be ready to get grilled</h1>
<p>Our interview panel consisted of Sam Altman, Geoff Ralston and Garry Tan. From the moment we walked in the room (before we even sat down!) we started getting grilled. I’ve heard some people describe the interviews as being a bit of a “stress test” seeing how you deal with highly intense situations. Each interview panel is different, and you should expect the style of the interview to be tailored to the people delivering it. Some are more “lean in”, while others are a bit more passive. The substance of the interviews is the same, so if you’re really prepared it shouldn’t matter too much who interviews you.</p>
<h1 id="beamasterofyourowndomain">Be a master of your own domain</h1>
<p>The YC partners are one of the most intelligent, experienced groups of people I’ve ever had the chance of working with. Generally speaking, no matter what domain you’re in, one of the YC partners will know at least as much — if not more — about it than you. As such, it’s crucial that you aren’t just a master of your own product, but the industry around it. This isn’t just true for your YC interview, but is important for your company’s overall success. Unfortunately, this isn’t something that you can “cram for” in a few day window, so if you’re green to your industry make sure you have a good story to tell.</p>
<h1 id="makesureeveryonespeaks">Make sure everyone speaks</h1>
<p>Y Combinator emphasizes the strength of the founding team above most other things. As such, it’s crucial that each member of the team is equally prepared for the interviews. Everyone should have the chance to speak and should maintain the same level of polish. For us, we decided ahead of time who on the team would answer which sorts of questions, and agreed that I would answer any questions where it wasn’t clear who else should talk. Generally speaking, there will be one person that answers most of the time, but it’s important no one tries to, “run away with the show.” Teamwork in the interview is as important as it is in the office.</p>
<h1 id="haveademobutdontexpecttoshowit">Have a demo, but don’t expect to show it</h1>
<p>I’ve heard many people debate whether the interviews should include a demo or not. The general convention is that the partners are more interested in hearing people talk about the thing, as opposed to seeing the thing itself. That said, there seems to be no consistency as to whether a team actually gets to show a demo. In our case, we were introducing a new concept that was too abstract for most people to understand so we had a &lt;30 second demo in place to make it clear exactly what we were talking about. We were able to show it, but only after trying about 3–4 times :). So, don’t rely on your demo as a crutch to tell your story.</p>
<p>The YC interview process is as challenging as it is invigorating, and I hope these 6 tips help you in your journey. Questions/feedback? Find me on Twitter <a href="http://twitter.com/jmilinovich">@jmilinovich</a></p>]]></description><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/ace-yc-interview</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/ace-yc-interview</guid><category><![CDATA[Dan Abramov]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[John Milinovich]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Good Idea, Bad Startup]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I had the privilege of being a guest lecturer at UCLA earlier this year to their Economics 106E: Startups class. It’s incredibly rewarding to be able to give back to my alma mater and help inspire/educate the next generation of entrepreneurs.</p>
<p>Every time I give a presentation like this, I am careful to balance the “goods and the bads” of living the startup life.. It’s a major red flag to me when people want to join startups because they’re, “cool”- it feels like a professional obligation to share the ups and downs of the journey.</p>
<p>I hope you enjoy watching this presentation as much as I enjoyed delivering it:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JnrpXGUWvs4" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/CoEfjVWEwxAOwf" width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>]]></description><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/good-bad-startup</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/good-bad-startup</guid><category><![CDATA[Dan Abramov]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[John Milinovich]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[7 lessons learned growing from 4 to 20 people]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>In URX’s first 2 years, we grew from 4 co-founders to a 20-person engineering, product and business team. With this growth, many of our internal processes and communication channels broke. It didn’t feel like we were moving as fast as we were before, and it took longer to get everyone on the same page.</p>
<h1 id="howcanwegrowstartupsasefficientlyaslivingorganisms">How can we grow startups as efficiently as living organisms?</h1>
<p>After analyzing our current processes, I came up with a new set of tenets that guide how I operate as a CEO. Thanks to the way communication overhead scales exponentially as a team grows, I expect to have to revisit these continuously along our growth curve.</p>
<p>Here are the 7 lessons I learned growing URX from 4 to 20 people.</p>
<h1 id="lesson1learntodelegate">Lesson 1: Learn to delegate.</h1>
<p>Learn the difference between things that are important enough for someone to do, and things that you should do. As a founding CEO in a growing company, your job changes continuously and success is determined in part by how quickly one can delegate responsibilities to others.</p>
<p>Generally speaking, as soon as you’d consider yourself, “good at something” you should hire someone to do it, or have someone else on the team own it. It’s important to keep your time free to find the, “unknown unknowns.”</p>
<p>Ben Horowitz talks more about this in <a href="http://www.bhorowitz.com/do_you_feel_pressure_or_do_you_apply_pressure">Do You Feel Pressure Or Do You Apply Pressure</a>.</p>
<h1 id="lesson2stayhighlyleveraged">Lesson 2: Stay highly leveraged.</h1>
<p>As a CEO, it is your responsibility to balance enabling your team to stay focused on execution while still having time to triage the most important issues in your business. It requires a high degree of discipline making sure that your time is always well spent.</p>
<p>For me, I gained a lot of leverage when I learned to say no. Whether it be internal meetings, “coffee invites”, or decisions you think others should make- learn to say no.</p>
<p>Jessica Stillman talks more about this in <a href="http://www.inc.com/jessica-stillman/why-and-how-to-stop-being-too-nice.html">Why You Need to Stop Being So Nice</a>.</p>
<h1 id="lesson3ownyourschedule">Lesson 3: Own your schedule.</h1>
<p>It’s well known that time is everyone’s most limited resource. This is even more true as a startup CEO, as there is never any shortage of things that, “could” be done. It’s crucial that you clearly define your priorities and reflect that in how you spend your time.</p>
<p>For me, a part of this was doubling down on becoming an email machine. I pride myself on being an email expert that is able to process 100's of emails per day using a combination of filters, rules, and reminders. My calendar’s been referred to as the, “Mona Lisa” of calendars — ok, maybe that’s just what I call it — and I’ve really taken pride in my productivity. I’ve developed my own “stack” that includes products like SaneLater, ClaraLabs and Boomerang.</p>
<p>David Allen talks more about this in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0143126563">Getting Things Done</a>.</p>
<h1 id="lesson4manageyouremotions">Lesson 4: Manage your emotions.</h1>
<p>As a founding CEO, your emotions are amplified throughout the organization. Everyone looks to the founders to know whether things are going well or not. The worst thing that could happen is you spook the team because you’re having a bad day. Whether you like it or not, you are the barometer for the company’s anxiety level.</p>
<p>The hardest part of building a startup is how quickly things change. It’s an emotional rollercoaster, and if not managed well will get the best of you. For me, this involves trying to live an integrated life that also leaves time for loved ones, working out, writing, sleeping and friends.</p>
<p>Ben Horowitz talks more about this in <a href="http://www.bhorowitz.com/what_s_the_most_difficult_ceo_skill_managing_your_own_psychology">Managing Your Own Psychology</a>.</p>
<h1 id="lesson5repeatyourself">Lesson 5: Repeat yourself.</h1>
<p>As a team grows, it becomes increasingly difficult to keep everyone on the same page. Make a point to repeat yourself and hammer home the company’s goals and vision through well-defined communication channels. Invest into well-maintained internal documentation- you can never have “too good” of an internal knowledge base.</p>
<p>At URX, I send a Monday email to start the week, and we do an all-team retro on Fridays where we talk through our goals, successes, launches, announcements, and wins for the week. We’ve built this into a part of our culture, and our Weekly Retro is a highlight of the week.</p>
<p>Peter Drucker talks more about this in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Effective-Executive-Definitive-Harperbusiness/dp/0060833459">The Effective Executive</a>.</p>
<h1 id="lesson6alignyourvisionwithyourgoals">Lesson 6: Align your vision with your goals.</h1>
<p>Make your company’s vision tangible by connecting it to actionable goals. In parallel, gut check that every goal is on the right scalars and vectors to help you properly measure success against your mission. Be careful not to overly optimize for either the near- or long-term.</p>
<p>At URX, we’re building a very complex technology, and I’ve learned first-hand the importance of having a clearly defined vision that the team can rally around. A well-defined mission statement is the only way a leadership team can build a cohesive plan that is aligned across the company. This plan can be used to then define your team’s goals, priorities and hiring needs.</p>
<p>Jim Collins talks more about this in <a href="http://www.jimcollins.com/lab/hedgehog/p2.html">The Hedgehog Concept</a>.</p>
<h1 id="lesson7knowyourprecedents">Lesson 7: Know your precedents.</h1>
<p>The beauty of the software industry is that it is built on the shoulders of giants. Whether we like it or not, our world is framed within the work of those that came before us.</p>
<p>It’s important to take a step back from the day-to-day to put your company and your problems into the broader context of the world around us. Practically speaking, this means that you’re likely not the first person to face some seemingly obscure problem. Chances are, some abstraction of the same type of challenge have been dealt with before.</p>
<p>URX is creating a new kind of marketplace for mobile commerce built with a technology that has never existed before. That said, I consider myself a student of the precedents for all facets of our business. From the history of how the internet was born, to the early days of search engines, to emerging mobile business models and their desktop equivalent- I strive to maximize the potential of URX by deeply understanding the world around us.</p>
<p>Kevin Owocki talks more about this in <a href="http://owocki.com/running-a-startup-youre-standing-on-the-shoulders-of-giants/">Running a Startup? You’re standing on the shoulders of giants</a>.</p>]]></description><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/4-to-20</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/4-to-20</guid><category><![CDATA[Dan Abramov]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[John Milinovich]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[People and Pine Cones- URX’s Y Combinator Story]]></title><description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>“Andrew, this is it — we’ve got the right team, and the timing’s perfect. If we don’t go for this now, we will regret it for the rest of our lives.” I could feel him thinking through the silence. “Alright dude, I’m in. Let’s talk to Nate and James and make this happen.”</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="decidingtogoforit">Deciding to Go for It</h1>
<p>It was a Friday afternoon in mid-January when Andrew, Nate, James and I went from being close friends to co-founders. Looking back, we had no idea what we were getting ourselves into, but our excitement and eagerness was enough to get us started.</p>
<p>I had just stepped out of a meeting with <a href="http://www.ted.com/speakers/bruno_bowden.html">Bruno Bowden</a>, an angel investor I met out of sheer coincidence: after a night out at bars, I dropped my credit card in front of Bruno’s apartment while getting out of a cab. A few days later, I got a LinkedIn message from him telling me he’d found my card. Being the opportunist that I am, I used this as a chance to meet Bruno and pitch him on a few ideas that Andrew, Nate, James and I were working on.</p>
<p>One week, one prototype and two all-nighters later, Bruno became our first angel investor and our journey began.</p>
<p>This experience solidified one of my theories about how the world works: <strong>opportunities present themselves in the most curious of manners and it’s each of our responsibilities to create our own luck.</strong></p>
<h1 id="foundingtoycombinatorthefirst90days">Founding to Y Combinator: the first 90 days.</h1>
<p>On my first day as, “John Milinovich, Startup CEO” I was shell-shocked. I stared at an empty GMail inbox, unsure of where to start. The novelty quickly faded to the reality of the situation: I needed help. <strong>In the early days of a startup, you are battling inertia: how do you force something into existence that doesn’t exist yet?</strong></p>
<p>I reached out to all of the mentors, friends and peers whose opinions I trusted to better understand how to get started. I was humbled by people’s response- <strong>people were so excited that I was going after my dreams and were willing to do whatever they could to help out.</strong> This led to several introductions, including to potential customers, investors and advisors.</p>
<p>At first, I was scared to share our idea with people. What if they didn’t like our product? What if they thought it wasn’t useful? What if they actually wanted to use it? I didn’t feel we were ready yet, but decided to put ourselves out there anyways.</p>
<p>This process taught me the most valuable lesson I learned early on: no matter what you’re building or “how early” you are in your development, <strong>it is never too early to start talking to potential customers.</strong> Customers (or users, in B2C companies) are the lifeblood of startups, and step 0 is to understand their problems and feel their pain. The more customers you speak with, the more perspective you gain — if you hear the same things multiple times, it’s probably something you should take into account.</p>
<p>In mid-April, I had the chance to meet <a href="http://chartio.com/about/dave">Dave Fowler</a>, the CEO of Chartio. Chartio was one of our neighbors in South Park, and had gone through YC a few years prior. It was a beautiful day outside, so we decide to walk around the Park. We ran into <a href="http://www.maxmullen.com/">Max Mullen</a>, one of the founders of Instacart (also in YC) and we hit it off right away. I shared a bit about what we were working on at URX, and within 5 minutes Max said, “Yep, that sounds awesome — we would totally use this, sign us up.” <strong>Serendipity had played its hand again, and we had just landed our first customer.</strong> Our product wasn’t fully built yet, but Max was committed to working with us to fully help us understand Instacart’s needs.</p>
<p>By this point, we had been invited to interview for the Summer 2013 class of Y Combinator and decided to, “make our own luck” and talk to as many YC founders as possible to get a grasp on the interview process. Bruno introduced us to <a href="http://www.sumonsadhu.com/">Sumon Sadhu</a>, who founded Snaptalent out of YC’s S’08 class. Sumon is, single handedly, the most talented strategist and persuasive communicator that I’d ever met. He taught us how the Y Combinator interview process works and hammered it into our heads that, <strong>no matter what, we need to clearly articulate our 5 Main Points in our interview.</strong> We boiled down the entirety of “Why we should be in YC” to five bullet points and committed them to memory.</p>
<p>A few days later we interviewed with <a href="http://ycombinator.com/people.html">Geoff Ralston, Sam Altman, and Garry Tan</a> and it was the <a href="http://sharpshoot.blogspot.com/2009/04/so-you-got-y-combinator-interview-now.html">most intense 10 minutes of our lives</a>. The interviews are as difficult as they are made out to be, but we crushed it. We got our points across and walked out confident that we had made a good impression. (In retrospect, I’m proud that all of the YC partners we interviewed with <a href="http://www.techcrunch.com/2013/10/16/urx-ads/">ended up becoming investors</a> in URX, along with Sumon).</p>
<h1 id="ycombinatorthe100dayjourney">Y Combinator: The 100 Day Journey</h1>
<p>Getting into Y Combinator was a dream come true. Like most young founders, the initial appeal of the program was based on its prestige and the opportunity to quickly gain access to the highest rung in Silicon Valley. <strong>For a group of people who understand the value of people and relationships, we knew we were on the right path.</strong></p>
<p>We’d all read Paul Graham’s essays, watched countless YouTube videos about YC, and spent too much time on HackerNews. None of that prepared us for the first time we went on a walk up and down Pioneer Way with PG. After getting into YC but before starting the program, PG meets with all of the startups in the batch. We gave him our quick pitch, and after quickly digesting it he told us that, <strong>“We have the opposite problem that most startups face. The opportunity created being able to link into the middle of mobile apps is so big it’s scary. Your challenge is not going to be whether this can be a billion dollar idea, but making sure you don’t get swallowed by it.”</strong> Before this we were confident in the opportunity in front of us, but didn’t fully digest how big it could be until hearing it come from PG. This block walk set the tone for the rest of YC- <em>how can we continue to be so big, we’re scary?</em></p>
<p>At the end of our meeting, PG told us that we need to change our name. It was too generic and not very interesting or differentiated. We spent 20 minutes brainstorming names that better represented our vision than AdLast (our name at the time), and quickly came up with a short-list of 10. URX was at the top of the list but was taken by someone else and had no clear indication of being for sale. We felt like we were at a loss, and admittedly thought we had a lot more important things to worry about than our name.</p>
<p>About a month later, we reported to duty for the first Tuesday dinner at YC. During our first group office hours (a bi-weekly format where 6 startups meet with 2 partners for an hour to discuss updates and challenges), I was introduced to Garry and Geoff outside the scope of our first 10-minute grilling. It’s amazing how similar most early-stage startup problems are to each other, despite all of the surface differences between companies. During that first meeting, Geoff asked a question that has stuck with URX and is now a part of how we evaluate ourselves: <strong>What are your bottlenecks to scaling?</strong> At any given point, a startup’s growth is inhibited by one of a few things- getting more customers, finding the right market, scaling operations, or technical debt- and by keeping a close pulse on which of these is the largest constraint gives a good perspective on where startups should be applying their limited resources.</p>
<p>During YC, every startup is paired with one of the partners to meet with frequently for 1:1 office hours. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Buchheit">Paul Buchheit</a>, the creator of GMail, AdSense and Friendfeed, was our partner. In that first meeting together, we talked about our roadmap, what our customers were saying, and where we saw the biggest immediate opportunity. At the time, we had built a deeplink open source framework and a “bitly for deeplinks,” but had identified that deeplink retargeting was going to be the next frontier. The technology behind a retargeting platform (on either mobile or desktop), is non-trivial to say the least, and during that first meeting <strong>PB made us realize that startups don’t get huge by focusing on small wins, but by going for the gold. He told us to stop talking about it and just go do it.</strong> We started building and selling our retargeting solution, and quickly realized he was right.</p>
<p>We received an email from PG about a month into YC telling us he’d like to meet because it had been a while since we’d talked last. Excited by the chance to show PG what we’ve built, we booked office hours and prepped what we wanted to talk about. On the familiar walk around Pioneer Way, PG stopped mid-sentence to bend down and pick something up off the ground. It was a mini pine cone from the redwood tree that towered above us. <strong>“Startups are like this pine cone,” he told us. “All of them start small and look the same, but only a few will ever realize their full potential.”</strong> He handed me the pine cone, and we kept walking. (In case you’re wondering, yes, I still have that pine cone). We continued sharing our plans and he simply shrugged and told us, <strong>“Do what will make you the most money first. Use that as your guiding light.”</strong> So simple, but more true than we knew at the time.</p>
<p>Towards the end of the meeting, PG gave us a hard time for not yet changing our name from AdLast. We’d looked into it, we told him, but the name wasn’t available. I could see (and hear) his disappointment, and <strong>quickly realized that my number one priority had just become our rebrand.</strong> 20 minutes later, I was on the phone with the current owner of the name URX and by the time we showed up at the next Tuesday dinner, we were URX.</p>
<h1 id="demodayandbeyond">Demo Day and Beyond</h1>
<p>Demo Day is the culmination of the YC experience. It is the reason for the massive time pressure most startups feel during the program and is usually the first time most talk to investors. We had elected to skip the traditional YC PR push about our product in favor of collecting more data, writing the case studies and honing our messaging. In our case, PG also recommended that we stay, “off the record” at Demo Day, meaning that even though we presented no one was allowed to talk about us. This is not the right idea for most startups, but it <a href="http://www.uncrunched.com/2013/10/08/unveiling-stealth-y-combinator-startup-urx">turned out being great for us</a>. It let us control our own messaging and focus on better understanding the story that we wanted to tell.</p>
<p>I feel fortunate to have been able to pull together our syndicate of investors in 2 ½ weeks. We had about 40 meetings and ended up raising from 31 investors. I didn’t sleep very much and probably took a few years off of my life, but it was well worth it. We had raised about ⅔ of our allocation in the week leading up to Demo Day and were able to filter through the inbound interest post-Demo Day to be very efficient with our meeting schedules. As <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/fr.html">PG says</a>, <strong>once you find your first investors, the rest will follow</strong>- this couldn’t have been more true for us.</p>
<p>Now that we’re a <a href="http://www.techcrunch.com/2013/10/16/urx-ads/">fully funded</a>, rapidly growing company, it feels amazing to be able to focus back on our <a href="http://takingpitches.com/2012/09/22/elon-musk-the-role-of-analogy-and-reasoning-from-first-principles-in-disruptive-entrepreneurship/">first principles</a>. Not much has changed- we are still “StartupHard,” still focus on our one thing, and are consistently obsessed with scaling and simplifying.</p>
<p>On a weekly if not daily cadence, I make sure to take a step back from things to fully appreciate the reality of the situation. I feel incredibly fortunate to have the chance to work with a rockstar team and have the chance to build something incredible. As my co-founder Andrew recently said, “It’s an interesting challenge to be fully focused on executing while still having the time to appreciate how much has changed in our lives.” <strong>It’s so easy to focus on climbing the mountain in front of us that we often forget to look at how far we’ve already come.</strong> We have our work cut out for us, but I am incredibly proud of the progress URX has made over the course of the last 9 months.</p>
<p>We’re not sure what’s around the corner for us, but we know that we will be ready for it when it happens.</p>]]></description><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/urx-yc</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/urx-yc</guid><category><![CDATA[Dan Abramov]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[John Milinovich]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1 year, 11 months at Google University]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I feel so fortunate to have spent the last 1 year, 11 months as a student at the most forward thinking company in the world. Working at Google, I was surrounded with incredibly talented people solving difficult problems in a culture of creativity, learning and personal growth.</p>
<p>Today is my last day at Google and, while I am incredibly sad to leave, I am, “uncomfortably excited” about what the future holds. The relationships, experience and skills that I gained during my time at Google have given me the confidence to pursue my dreams of being a startup co-founder.</p>
<p>Some of the most stimulating conversations that I‘ve ever had have been over the amazing food at Beta, Charlie’s or Big Table. I will miss the lunchtime talks and impassioned diatribes more than anything else. There’s no way to explain the culture more than just, “Googley” — unique viewpoints, analytical thinking and creativity flowed through the hallways and was palpable on campus.</p>
<p>Google lets its employees work at an incredible scale at all levels in the company. There are very few organizations that impact as many people and make as much money as Google, and it is absolutely marveling how they make it all work. I’ve had the opportunity to launch new products, build internal programs with global impact, patent new technologies and manage technology partnerships for products used by tens of millions of people. I worked on 20% projects, attended Author Talks, learned Linux, answered customer support questions and filed bugs. Google gave me the freedom to identify and fix the problems with the most impact.</p>
<p>My favorite perk from Google is their investment into the continued education of its employees. Google offers courses to help develop and round out Googlers’ skillsets to help them grow as professionals and individuals. I was able to structure my own curriculum and took 100+ hours of coursework in Python, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Meditation, Strategic Thinking, Creative Thinking, Negotiations, Data Visualization and Building Authentic Relationships. I received an excellent education and was exposed to new ways of thinking about technology, business and myself all while in the confines of the ‘Plex.</p>
<p>I will always love Google and cherish my memories of my time in Mountain View. I spent some of the most difficult times in my life as a Google employee, and the way they took care of me is something that I will never forget. Google truly cares about its employees and its users and will continue to prosper as long as they keep the spirit alive.</p>
<p>Thank you, Google.</p>]]></description><link>https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/google</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.jmilinovich.com/blog/google</guid><category><![CDATA[Dan Abramov]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[John Milinovich]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>